Thomas L. Lentz collection on the history of cell biology and anatomy at Yale
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Thomas L. Lentz collection on the history of cell biology and anatomy at Yale
1899-2015
Ms Coll 57
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
10
All are small flat boxes of varying sizes..
Thomas L. Lentz served as professor of cell biology and associate dean of admissions at Yale School of Medicine. The collection contains autobiographical material on Dr. Lentz, his histories of cell biology and of histology at Yale, and reprints of his articles. Also included are teaching materials for Lentz's laboratory course on histology, published materials related to the Department of Cell Biology, and photographs of faculty members and students.
Lentz, Thomas L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Thomas L. Lentz, 2015. Some materials donated earlier.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Related Materials
Thomas L. Lentz's collection of microscopes and historical glass microscope slides has been donated to the Scientific Instrument Collection at the Peabody Museum at Yale.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas L. Lentz was born in 1939 in Toledo, Ohio, attended Cornell University for three years where he majored in zoology and became interested in the study of hydra, and then entered Yale School of Medicine in 1960. In his first year of medical school, he joined the laboratory of cell biologist Russell J. Barnett who encouraged him to continue the study of hydra using techniques of cell biology, especially electron microscopy. Lentz decided he was more interested in research than medical practice, and chose not do a residency after graduating from medical school. Instead he joined the Department of Anatomy in 1964 as an instructor and rose through the ranks to become Professor of Cell Biology in 1985. His chief research interests were in neurobiology and cell biology. Lentz published three scientific books, as well as two books related to his hometown of Killington. He taught medical school courses in Microscopic Anatomy, later called Cell Biology, which included laboratory exercises. In 1968, Lentz became a member of the Committee on Admissions of the Medical School, and in 1972 chair of the committee. His title eventually became Associate Dean of Admissions. Under his tenure, the number of women and African-Americans admitted to the medical school greatly increased. After his retirement in 2006, he developed his interest in history.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains a brief autobiography, curriculum vitae, annual reports of accomplishments at Yale, and reprints of his articles; Lentz's histories of the Department of Cell Biology and of histology at Yale; published materials on the Department of Cell Biology; two volumes of photographs of faculty and students; and extensive material on the microbiology/histology course with laboratory exercises that Lentz taught, including lectures, laboratory manuals, and images. Of special interest are two microscope slide kits of the types loaned to students who were taking the laboratory course from the 1930s to about 2003.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: 1. Thomas L. Lentz biographical materials and publications. 2. Microscopic anatomy and histology teaching materials. 3. Historical materials on the Department of Anatomy and the Department of Cell Biology. 4.Photographs -- Department of Cell Biology.
Anatomy -- Study and teaching; Cytology -- Study and teaching; Cells -- Morphology; Electron microscopy; Histology -- Study and teaching; Medical education -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Medical laboratories -- Connecticut; Medical students -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Compact discs; Laboratory manuals; Lectures; Photographs; Reprints; Slides (microscopy); Microbiologists; Neurobiologists; Barnett, Russell Joffree, -1989; Burr, Harold Saxton, 1889-; Crelin, Edmund S., 1923-; Farquhar, Marilyn G.; Ferris, H. B. (Harry Burr), 1865-1940; Forbes, Thomas Rogers, 1911-1988; Gardner, William U. (William Ullman), 1907-1988; Jamieson, James D.; Lentz, Thomas L.; Palade, G. E.; Yale University. Department of Anatomy; Yale University. Department of Cell Biology; Yale University. School of Medicine -- History; Crelin, Edmund S., 1923-
- Thomas L. Lentz biographical materials and publications, Series I
  - Thomas L. Lentz biographical sketch, curriculum vita, and annual reports on his accomplishments at Yale, 2012 (Box 1, Item 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Typescript, 99 pages, containing a biographical sketch that goes beyond his scientific career; a curriculum vitae; and annual report (to his Department?) on his research activities, teaching activities, administrative activities, lectures, and publications, 1965-2000.
  - Detailed description of donations to the Historical Library, 2015 (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Published and unpublished histories of cell biology and histology at Yale, 2011 (Box 1, Item 3)
    Thomas L Lentz, "History of the Department of Cell Biology at Yale School of Medicine, 1813-2010," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine 84 (2011): 69-82, photocopy of published article.
    Thomas L. Lentz, "History of the Department of Cell Biology, Yale University School of Medicine, 1813-2010," typescript, 2003, updated 2011, longer version of published history.
    Thomas L. Lentz, "History of Histology at the Yale School of Medicine," typescript, copyright August 2011.
  - Reprints of scientific articles by Thomas Lentz, 1960-1974 (Box 2)
    Includes Dr. Thomas Lentz's list of articles numbered 1 to 41.
  - Reprints of scientific articles by Thomas Lentz, 1975-2011 (Box 3)
    Includes Dr. Lentz's list of articles numbered 42 to 104.
- Microscopic anatomy and histology teaching materials, Series II
  - Thomas L. Lentz, Cell Fine Structure, Anatomy 102a, Cell Biology, 1969 (Box 4, Item 1)
    Photocopied text and illustrations in a binder.
  - Thomas L. Lentz and James D. Jamieson, Molecules to Systems, Cell Biology and Microscopic Anatomy Syllabus and Laboratory Outline, 2003 (Box 4, Item 2)
    General
    "Revised 2003." For 2003-2004.
  - Medical Histology Laboratory Workbook, Yale University School of Medicine, 2009 (first edition) (Box 4, Item 3-4)
    2 copies. By Michael Peluso and John Hsi-en Ho, Peter A. Takizawa, Thomas Lentz, James D. Jamieson. "Molecules to Systems Integrated Curriculum."
  - Microscopic Anatomy/ Histology student slide set, ca. 1930- ca.1950 (Box 5, Item 1)
    Separated Materials
    Each student in the histology laboratory would be loaned a set of slides on which they would be quizzed. The set is numbered 69 and consists of 70 glass microscope slides in a box. This type of set was used from the 1930s to the 1950s. Dr. Lentz provided a key to the slides.
  - Microscopic Anatomy/ Histology laboratory student slide set, ca. 1950-2003
    This set of glass slides in a wooden box is numbered 111. According to Dr. Lentz, this type of set was "used from about 1950 to 2003, updated in 1980." "Each student was provided with a set to use during the course." Key to slides included.
  - Album of compact disks related to teaching, mostly 2002-2011 (Box 6, Item 1)
    Album of compact discs containing images used in teaching the histology laboratory, Cell Biology 502a. The histological images were taken beginning in 1965, and the electron micrographs were taken by Cell Biology faculty in the 1970s, and later scanned from slides. Included are Lentz's histology PowerPoint presentations for each laboratory session in 2002-3003 and 2003-2004; his PowerPoint introductions to histology laboratories, 2006-2011; images of the drawings in Thomas L. Lentz, Cell Fine Structure. Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders, 1971; Histology Qualifying Exam, Cell Biology 502, 2003; text of muscle and nervous system lectures by Thomas Lentz, 2002; text of Lentz's histories of cell biology and histology at Yale; and other sets of images on anatomy and histology, some of which may have been purchased.
- Historical materials on the Department of Anatomy and the Department of Cell Biology, Series III
  - Guides to graduate studies in Cell Biology, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Yale University, Graduate Studies in Cell Biology, 1988, 2 copies.
    Yale University, Yale Graduate Program in Molecular Cell Biology, 1991.
  - Guides to the Combined Program in the Biological and Biomedical Sciences (BBS), 1999-2008 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Yale University, Combined Program in the Biological and Biomedical Sciences, 1999.
    Yale University. Combined Program in the Biological and Biomedical Sciences at Yale University, 2008-2010.
  - Department of Cell Biology news and events, 1984-2008 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Richard K. Gershon Memorial Lectureship; rabies virus research Yale Weekly Bulletin, December 1984. Thomas L. Lentz was one of the investigators in the rabies project.
    Invitation to a farewell reception for Marilyn G. Farquhar and George E. Palade, Feb. 23, 1990.
    "20 Years of Cell Biology at Yale," Cell Biology Department Newsletter, November, 1993.
    Cell Biology, LCME accreditation, 1994. Description of status of Department.
    Invitation to Cell Biology Holiday Party, December 14, 2001.
    Palade Lecture poster, Ari Helenius, "What viruses tell us about endocytosis," April 2, 2004.
    Cell Biology and Microbial Pathogenesis Retreat, October 28-29, 2004, program.
    Dean's Workshop, "Electron Microscopy in the Molecular Era: A World Inside the World You See," November 4, 2005 program.
    "Leading scientist is appointed new chair of Cell Biology," Medicine@Yale, 4[3] (July/August 2008): 1, 6. Article on James Rothman.
    Program of Cell Biology & Microbial Pathogenesis Retreat, 2004.
  - Department of Anatomy, description, 1924, and obituaries, 1924, 1940-2004 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    H. B. Ferris, "Yale University School of Medicine Department of Anatomy," Rockefeller Foundation, Methods Problems Med. Educ., First Series, 1924, 1-16.
    H. S Burr, "Harry Burr Ferris." Science, 92(1940): 499-500.
    D. H., "Harry Burr Ferris." Yale J. Biol. Med., 13(1940): 285-292. 2 copies
    D. H. "Harold Saxton Burr," Yale J. Biol. Med., 30(1957): 161-167. 2 copies.
    J. S. Nicholas, "Samuel Randall Detwiler (1890-1957)," Year Book of the American Philosophical Society (1959): 116-122.
    J. S. Nicholas, "Ross Granville Harrison – 1870-1959," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 32(1960): 407-412.
    J. S. Nicholas, "Ross Granville Harrison, Experimental Embryologist." Science 131(1960):337-339.
    J. S. Nicholas, "Ross Granville Harrison, 1870-1959," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 32[6] (1960): 407-412, and portrait frontispiece.
    J. S. Nicholas, "Ross Granville Harrison. January 13th 1870-September 30th, 1959," Anatomical Record, 137 (1960):160-162. Typescript of text.
    "Russell J. Barrnett, 65th year," brochure on where his many students are now.
    Russell J. Barrnett and Thomas H. Forbes, "William U. Gardner, 1907-1988," typescript.
    James D. Jamieson, "Russell Joffree Barrnett, 1920-1989," typescript.
    Frederic L. Holmes, "Thomas Rogers Forbes, 1911-1988," typescript.
    Program of memorial service for Russell J. Barrnett, October 13, 1989, brochure.
    "Professor Edmund Slocum Crelin, Jr., Ph.D., Sc.D.," obituary, Yale e-mail, 2004.
  - Correspondence regarding the Ferris Prize, 1933, 1937, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Correspondence of the faculty with the administration concerning changing the criteria for the H.B. Ferris Prize in dissection.
  - Selected articles by faculty of Departments of Anatomy and Cell Biology, 1899-1978 (Box 8)
    Includes selected reprints of Horst Oertel (1899), Harold Saxton Burr, H. B. Ferris, John Spangler Nicholas, Leon Stanfield Stone, Charles H. Sawyer, Russell J. Barrnett, and others,
- Photographs -- Department of Cell Biology, Series IV
  List by Thomas L. Lentz, M.D.
  This is a collection of photographs taken mostly at events of the Medical School, Department of Cell Biology, and Laboratory of Thomas L. Lentz between 1978 and 2005. Many faculty, medical students, and graduate students are illustrated. With negatives for most and names written on back of many photos.
  Outline
  Medical School and Students I (1979-1995) Medical School and Students II (12/95-00) Medical School and Students III (2000-2005) Department and Lab I (1966-3/89) Department and Lab II (Woods Hole, 87, 88, 89, 6/89-6/91) Department and Lab III (Picnics I (87, 88, 89, 90, 91) Department and Lab IV (Woods Hole, 91) Department and Lab V (8/91-7/92) Department and Lab VI (9/92-10/94) Department and Lab VII (8/94-7/95) Department and Lab VIII (12/95-00) Department and Lab IX (1999)
  Medical School and Students I (1979-1995)
  Histology lab, 1979 Histology lab, 1983 Histology lab, 1984 Donna Klimowicz, 5/87 Second Year Show, 3/89 Histology lab, 1987 Graduation (George Bush), 5/91 Class of 1991 Student Affairs Christmas Party, 12/92 Histology lab, 1993 Chair's retreat, Mystic, CT, 7/95
  Medical School and Students II (12/95-00)
  Dorm Dinner, 12/95 Histology Lab, 12/5/95 Medical Student Christmas Party, 12/95 Louis' Lunch, 12/95 Louis' Lunch, 2/9/96 Second Year Show-1996 Christmas-1996, 1997 Misc. (Bob Gifford, Lynne Wootton) BioStep, Chatfield Hollow, 7/97, 7/98
  Medical School and Students III (2000-2005)
  Graduation, 5/22/2000 Histology Lab, TAC Building, 2003 Match Day, 3/2004 Graduation, 5/2004 TAs at Louis' Lunch, 5/2004 Histology Lab, TAC Building, 2005
  Department and Lab I (1966-3/89)
  Thomas L. Lentz, 1966 George Palade Nobel Party, 9/74 Thomas L. Lentz, Janice Chester, 1978 Christmas Party, 1978 Debbie Fine, John Neal, Christmas, 1980 Christmas Party, 1981 Christmas Party, 1983 Birthday Party, 1983 Party for Jonny Gershoni, 1983 Birthday Party, 3/89
  Department and Lab II (1987-6/91)
  Department Retreat, Woods Hole, Fall, 1987 Woods Hole, 5/88 Abbot's & Woods Hole, 4/89 Department Softball Team, 6/89 Abbot's, Noank, CT, 5/90 Nancy Walworth Wedding, 7/90 Andy Shyjan's Party, 2/22/91 Dee-Dee Donnelly-Roberts, 5/91 Thomas L. Lentz, 5/91 Chick's, West Haven, 6/91
  Department and Lab III (1987-1991)
  Picnic for Paul Wilson and Donna Klimowicz, 5/87 Picnic for department at Tom Lentz's house, 6/88 Picnic, 5/89 Picnic, 6/1/90 Woodcutting, 12/90 Picnic, 6/8/91
  Department and Lab IV (5/91)
  Department Retreat, Woods Hole, 5/91
  Department and Lab V (8/91-7/92)
  Fenway Park, 8/21/91 Heike Müeller's Party, 8/24/91 Heike QE 2 Heike, Germany, 1/92 Louis' after Bob Bowser's Defense 2/14/92 Party for Bob, Novicks', 2/15/92 New Haven scenes Department picnic, 7/24/92
  Department and Lab VI (9/92-10/94)
  Retreat-Interlaken Inn, 9/92 Knicks, Madison Square Garden, 12/92 Department Picnic, Lighthouse Park, 7/93 Louis' Lunch, 12/9/93 Woodcutting 11/93 Yale Golf Course Woods Hole, 4/94 Woodcutting, 10/94
  Department and Lab VII (8/94-7/95)
  Party for Pat Brenwald, Guendalina Rossi, and Michelle Garrett at Novick's, 8/94 Lisa Dunbar's Wedding, 6/16/95 Trip to White Mountains, 7/29/95
  Department and Lab VIII (12/95-00)
  Nancy Walworth TAs at Louis' Lunch, 1/96 Brush Cutting, 11/96 Louis' Lunch, 1/97 Chatfield Hollow, 6/97, 7/97 Tom Lentz, 11/99 Graduation, 5/99
  Department and Lab IX (1999)
  Shannon Turley thesis defense parties, 3/31/99 Yale University Commencement, 5/24/99
  - Album of large photographs, Department of Cell Biology, 1893-2005; 1966-2005 (Box 9)
    Includes photographs of faculty members, laboratories, students using equipment, attendees at Gordon Research Conferences, and the white coat ceremony in August 2000. Nineteenth century images were copied from a nineteenth-century publication. Most photographs are 8 1/2 x 11 inches. A few at the end of the album are 4 x 6 inches.
  - Album of small photographs, Department of Cell Biology, 1966-2005 (Box 10)
    Photographs in the album are 3 1/2 x 5 inches and are well documented. The bulk of the photos are from the 1980s and 1990s. There are many informal pictures of students as well as of faculty. Topics include parties, picnics, departmental retreats at Woods Hole, student ceremonies like White Coat and Graduation, as well as some photographs of the Histology Laboratory.